all right so here I would like to talk
about is uh unintended consequences of
policies in the way that we actually set
up our social systems and in particular
I want to focus on the the notion of how
our homes shifted from being homes
shelter places where we live and raise
our families to assets and possibly
they're on their way back and for the
purposes of this particular video I'm
simply going to assume that everything
I'm going to report on is an unintended
consequence to the degree to which it's
an intended consequence of somebody's
actions it may very well be but I don't
care all right so I'm going to fast
forward through the history of the
Federal Reserve but the key insight here
is that the Federal Reserve the way or
at least one of the principal ways that
it tries to manage or modulate the
economy is through interest rates and
the way that it modulates the economy
through interest rates is that it
changes the rate at which banks can
borrow money
I'm simplified but I'd have to get this
in place to kind of get to the next
piece which makes it possible to have
more money coming to the economy and
when banks can bring more money into the
economy there's more economic activity
that could happen that they can fuel but
here's the thing banks don't have direct
access to the real economy right banks
don't buy widgets and they don't make
cars thanks loan money to people who do
that kind of stuff so when the Federal
Reserve is trying to increase activity
in the economy by lowering interest
rates what they're doing is they're
pushing on banks to be able to produce
more debt in the economy to get more to
make more loans alright fair enough
let's just I don't I'm not gonna
critique that just yet we're just going
to talk about the unintended
consequences of that particular approach
so when you look at the debt market the
bond market in the economy the biggest
piece by far is US Treasuries but I'm
gonna rule that out because that's not
productive well I mean in some sense
maybe it finances government activity
but I mean you can or that entirely you
know the two big chunks are
our corporate and mortgage in fact
mortgages is the bigger of those two so
home loans alright so when the when the
Fed is trying to get money into the
economy and it's telling banks ok money
is cheaper for you to make available
loan money out into the market you know
mark it up a bit and let it back out one
of the biggest funnels that they can put
that money into is in home loans so they
do right because there's only so many
bankers and they can only cut so many
deals and they can't you know they just
have to be able to figure out what are
the biggest chunks of the economy that
they could actually modify and interact
with by the way in the corporate side
this will typically show up and things
like large structured finance for MBA
for buyouts and acquisitions which is
one of the reasons why another
unintended consequences consolidation
it's just easier to write a billion
dollar check to get a big company to buy
another big company that is to try to
write like a billion one dollar checks
to a whole bunch of guys who are trying
to start up their own pizzas dance okay
so mortgages so now you have this this
notion and a need to move money into the
economy by promoting mortgages which of
course is about basically getting one
agent a person a home buyer to be able
to be financed to be able to buy a home
which of course then puts money in the
hands of the home seller but then in
principle at least rejects it back to
the economy in some fashion although of
course many of them buy new houses which
doesn't really have a whole lot of
impact on the real economy but a
characteristic of this is that it
increases the price of homes you have
this process where the need to inject
money into the Riesz economy has as a
consequence that it causes there to be
more money chasing after what is more
less relatively inflexible supply of
homes I'm not always obviously
construction can happen it does happen
for sure but it tends to increase the
price of homes okay so here's the next
piece when you've got a long enough
period of time where that policy has
been in place that the price of homes
has a very standard characteristic of up
and to the right which is just say it
becomes part of the zeitgeist part of
the the unassuming assumptions that
mortgage prices
relatively stable and slightly accretive
because we've actually been creating an
artificial vector of driving pressure
because that's a vector that we have for
putting money into the economy then you
get a secondary consequence which is
that mortgages in a particular
mortgage-backed securities begin to be
taken as relatively risk-free you begin
to assume that this condition that
you've been seeing for a long period of
time is a natural condition of the
universe and think it's a solid
foundation when in fact to some extent
it's an artifact of an unintended
consequence of one of our mechanisms of
managing the economy of the way that we
design that wreck the Fed had been
designed a different way if the Fed then
had the ability to say for example
deliver a ubi directly to people as
opposed to trying to moderate things
through banks then we have a different
set of unintended consequences but not
that one it's a little bit more esoteric
let's take a look at two forks on this
road as mortgages in particular
mortgage-backed securities become seen
as relatively risk-free they also then
become really high-quality collateral so
if I'm trying to engage in large
transactions one of the things that I
might do is I might hold mortgage-backed
securities and then I will use them as
collateral so I get debt leverage right
if I've got a million dollars of
mortgage securities and I go to the bank
and say had like a loan backed by this
as collateral they might say great I'll
give you 3 million for that that is
collateral so now I've got 3 million to
work with and of course in particular if
I use that 3 million to go out and buy
more property then that actually becomes
an asset that I could bring pump back in
as collateral so I get a feedback loop
where the ability to take this asset as
a super high quality low risk asset
creates a capacity to actually generate
more leverage which actually by the way
injects more risk into the system but
it's risky you don't see because it's
tapped to that asset and this is of
course the story of the movie the big
short we saw that happen in 2006 where
mortgage prices kept going up because
more money was pumped into the system
originally it was the Fed and lending
rates but then it actually was the fact
that because mortgages were seen as a
solid collateral debt was leveraged was
generated but that leverage was then
pumped back into the system
of course if I have three million
dollars and used that 30min dollars to
go out and buy more property then the
price of property goes up which to some
extent means the value of my collateral
just went up certainly I can mark it
that way I used to have a million
dollars with a property but now it's
worth fifteen one point five million
because the price of properties going up
guys come on my collateral is worth more
so now I can borrow more so I can vest
more so now I can borrow more when you
get a feedback loop where this happens
and this in fact actually did happen so
that's one secondary consequence so
let's now go to a tertiary consequence
and I'll actually slide sideways after
this to a kind of a fun ancillary
tertiary consequence now in this context
we're having this feedback loop where
prices are going up in lending rates and
leverage is being used then you get a
competitive landscape because the
bankers are competing to write loans
like that's what they do that's their
that's their their product right just
like cell phone manufacturers compete to
cell phones banks compete to sell loans
and where there's there's there's
there's a limited supply like there's a
lot of money that wants to get into
selling to writing loans that would
happen since they have to make better
terms and that a better term might be
for example giving more leverage to less
collateral so instead of getting three
million dollars per billion dollars in
collateral maybe I get four or five or
ten right and at the peak of the 2006
financial bubble leverage was starting
to go through the roof right because the
more promiscuous bankers that ones who
are willing to write the fastest hottest
cheapest loans got more business and
they made more money because of course
they don't make their money on a
particularly mortgage brokers to make
their money on the return of the loans
they make their money on the cutting of
the loan the selling of the look but
they just flip it and sell to somebody
else who packages it into a
mortgage-backed security or to some
other kind of object so you create an
economic system where there's a moral
hazard I believe is the term let's just
call it promiscuity become selected for
now of course that doesn't creates an
accelerated price of the asset cuz
there's just more money chasing what is
now a very hard strapped supply you
could try to you know cranes everywhere
trying to build buildings but they can't
keep up with the velocity of money cuz
finance moves fast okay so so then we do
is you get this rapidly accelerating
thing until something breaks at the top
some small per
Meishan becomes more fragile more
susceptible to small perturbations
because it's way out of her skis in
terms of leverage and then somebody
somewhere some small shift in price goes
down somebody is you know misses a
payment there's bankruptcy the you know
but in the case of 2006 the lending
terms just got so crazy that just
couldn't make any sense and something
you know small contraction the economy
cascades down and hits this thing but
then you have the type of fragile the
most promiscuous lenders are also the
most vulnerable leverage their way out
over their skis and then borrowers are
the most way over their skis so if I'm
gonna tend to one leverage and suddenly
the value of my asset base just went
down market the value of security of
mortgage-backed securities to went down
a little tiny bit
well my collateral just got worth less
so now I'm under collateralized so now I
have to sell some of my real asset
getting enough collateral will shoot
with that price prices down at the
margin just maybe like a tenth of a
point
but now when this thing is to have a
hyper efficient hyper competitive a
tenth of a point makes a difference that
cascades down alright so that same
steepness of a cent becomes a steep as a
descent so a tertiary unintended
consequence you actually create vastly
more volatile markets that have a
characteristic of prices going way up
and then having huge crashes when they
fall let me slide sideways a bit because
it's also very important because in this
process when the value of an object in
this case a home and the land it's
sitting on becomes financialized it
becomes an object of securities and
become something where money is moving
meaningfully significantly it shifts in
its meaning it shifts from an from a
home it shifts from a thing that
satisfies human needs a place that rain
keeps raining off your head and keeps
you warm to an asset it becomes a
financial object and that means people
begin to think of it as a financial
object it's called wealth effects right
if I can get people's homes to be more
valuable they feel like they're
wealthier which means by the way they'll
be willing to spend more money if I feel
rich I'm less worried about what how
much cash I have in the bank because
I've got a $500,000 home I'm rich so
fine I'll spend more money so we saw
that we saw this notion of the wealth
effects and was interesting is that we
not only we first noticed it then we
took advantage of it then we got
addicted to it
we actually had to get people feeling
more and more wealthy to keep that
wealth effect
to keep the flow of money going and so
then you get another negative feedback
loop if the price of the house starts to
go down not only do you start getting
the debt side of the market evaporating
but also the wealth effect you become so
addicted to starts to evaporate and
velocity of money collapses people like
oh I'm not rich anymore oh and I've
got no money in the bank oh I need
to change my behavior right so you get a
collapse on that direction then let's do
another one
this other one's kind of funky so let's
say you're trying to be an educator and
you're trying to make the educational
system better and let's say you've
actually got a whole new way of testing
a new testing infrastructure that
actually much more accurately evaluates
the quality of education in an
environment how well people have learned
the quality of students this is like a
lot better but it's different so then
you go to a school district and say hey
we'd like to give you this new
methodology we'll do it for free we're
awesome and it's gonna make it you're
gonna do a better job of teaching your
students would be smarter more capable
or more effective contributors to
society your tests will be more accurate
now like that sounds awesome so then
start talking about in the community and
some smart guy in the back probably a
mortgage broker goes what's this gonna
do to our existing test scores you say
well I mean it's gonna obsolete them
you're not going to need them anymore is
they're useless our testing
infrastructure is a lot better they go
yeah but here's the thing real estate
prices have a significant direct
connection to test scores if I've got
two neighborhoods that are roughly
equivalent in everything except for they
they broadcast their local schools
broadcast different qualities of test
scores then the one that has higher test
scores has higher prices more wealth the
prices the houses are worth more it's a
better neighborhood because of that
metric and guess what you find really
quick nobody's interested in buying your
new technology so a technology in the
educational domain that should actually
by hypothesis at least radically upgrade
the quality of education can't gets
accepted because we've been trained our
testing methodology to our home value
methodology and our whole
economy is now built on home values so
and I don't mean just like the
homeowners will get pissed if the home
prices go down the entire economy
collapses because we're so premise don
home prices being stable they always
going up you know if we have a small
shift in the price of homes the lending
market collapses because they become
hyper fragile the wealth effect Goes
Down and so the economy begins to shrink
and that collapses so this crazy Kuantan
area effect you might call it of the
fact that we designed our system so the
Federal Reserve tries to modify the
economy by reducing interest rates which
increases the or induces banks to be
more able and willing to loan money at a
cheaper price which causes more pressure
to push money in we only have a small
number of large valves corporate
securities and mortgage securities to
drop money into which increases the
price the value of the amount of money
chasing after homes which increases the
price of homes which creates all these
different secondary and tertiary side
effects and that's just the tip of the
iceberg so something to think about